Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.17
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series XVII. Ongoing Career
1993
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.17
59.5 Linear Feet
In May 1993 Dick Thornburgh returned to Washington, rejoining Kirkpatrick & Lockhart as counsel in their Washington office. That role has enabled Thornburgh to devote time to clients, and yet retain the opportunity to pursue outside interests and challenges which have been many and varied. For example, his foreign trips include visits to Taiwan, Russia, and several to Hong Kong, regarding the rule of law. Trips to Guatemala (regarding governmental corruption), to Nigeria (regarding federalism, interstate relations and other governance issues), and to Buenos Aires (on fighting corruption) are also well documented. Other trips abroad concern his continued dedication to the rights of persons with disabilities. Major challenges include, for example, his appointment as Examiner in the WorldCom bankruptcy proceedings, the largest ever filed, and his choice in 2004 by CBS to conduct an investigation into the "60 Minutes Wednesday" segment on President Bush's service in the Texas Air National Guard. During the 1990s he embarked upon a new mini-career on television as a legal commentator on subjects such as the O.J. Simpson case, and President Clinton issues. One constructive by-product of the horrific September 11 attacks on the World Trade Towers was a review for the National Academy of Public Administration of FBI plans for reorganization, a task force that Thornburgh was asked to chair, and additional service as a member of the FBI Director's Advisory Board. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998.
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Accruals
Additional material is being added on a regular basis to reflect Thornburgh's still active career.
Judges -- Selection and appointment -- United States; Pennsylvania -- Economic conditions; Personal papers; Russia (Federation); Government; Environment; Politics; Social action; Business and Industry; Hong Kong (China); Larry King live (Television program); Late edition (Television program); 60 minutes II (Television program); Lawyers -- United States; Rule of law; Home rule -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; White collar crimes -- United States; Political corruption -- United States; Child pornography; Internet pornography; WorldCom (Firm); International Republican Institute; American Bar Association; National Academy of Public Administration; National Organization on Disability (U.S.); Columbia Broadcasting System, inc.; Cable News Network; Washington Legal Foundation. Legal Policy Advisory Board; Russian-American Institute for Law and Economics; U.S. Committee on Hong Kong; World Committee on Disability; Thornburgh, Dick; Thornburgh, Ginny (Judson); Yakovlev, Veniamin; King, Larry; Blitzer, Wolf; Simpson, O. J. -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Rather, Dan; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation. Director's Advisory Board; United States. Independent Counsel Reauthorization Act of 1987; Kirkpatrick & Lockhart Nicholson Graham; Urban Institute; State Science & Technology Institute
- Ongoing Career, 1993; XVII.
  Scope and Contents note
  Following his sojourn at the United Nations, at the end of February 1993, Dick Thornburgh returned to Washington, his twenty-five year career in public office at an end, and ready for what he termed a role as "useful citizen."
  The quest of a new baseball commissioner came his way in May 1993, and friends who knew of his long-standing love of baseball encouraged his interest. Although he survived several cuts, his final contribution to the matter was an op-ed piece in the Wall Street Journal, in August 1994. Meanwhile, after scrutiny of alternatives, he decided to return, once again, to Kirkpatrick & Lockhart as counsel in their Washington Office. That role has enabled Thornburgh to devote over half his time to clients, and yet retain the opportunity to pursue other outside interests developed over the years.
  These interests have been many and varied, most of which are well documented in these files and frequently draw on Thornburgh's previous experience, both in government generally and at the United Nations in particular. A major topic, for example, has been the rule of law in developing countries and others emerging from Soviet domination. "If these nations were to see more democracy, respect for human rights and market-oriented economies ... the rule of law was an absolute sine qua non. Without it, free elections, corruption-free government and due process would be impossible ... Thus I became a veritable missionary for the rule of law" (Evidence, p. 336).
  The section here on foreign trips includes visits to Taiwan, Russia, and several to Hong Kong, all regarding the rule of law. Other trips to Guatemala (regarding governmental corruption), to Nigeria (regarding federalism, interstate relations and other governance issues), to Buenos Aires (on fighting corruption), are well documented here as well. In addition, other trips abroad concern his continued dedication to the rights of persons with disabilities, particularly in a return trip to Korea where Thornburgh and his wife, Ginny, discussed issues of religion and disability. "Our visit left us feeling that Korea had a long way to go in affording dignity to its citizens with disability, but we were heartened that so many people of goodwill, particularly within the religious communities, were trying to meet those challenges" (Evidence, p. 346).
  Other challenges presented themselves, for example, examination of World Bank's "mechanisms to deal with fraud and corruption connected with its lending" (Evidence, p. 347), and involvement with civil justice reform, growing out of a report on the subject prepared by the Department of Justice in 1991 for the President's Council on Competitiveness. Thornburgh's interest in science and technology which dated back to the Ben Franklin Partnership of Governor days further took center stage from early to mid 1990s, and concern about product liability and caps on punitive damages are well expressed in his op-eds on the subject, all of which are available here online.
  Also, during the 1990s, he "embarked upon a new mini-career as a television 'personality' ... The first call came on July 6, 1994, from the producer of Larry King Live, asking if [he] would consider a guest appearance that night to discuss some of the legal issues in the O.J. Simpson case ... One television appearance led to others; in total [he] appeared forty-five times on CNN to examine various aspects of the Simpson case" (Evidence, p. 352). This led to further television appearances in connection with high-profile cases such as: murders of JonBenet Ramsey and Chandra Levy, President Clinton's "misadventures" (Evidence, p. 353), and other appearances to discuss varying legal issues, over many years, on CNN's Late Edition, hosted by Wolf Blitzer. "Despite the sometimes long hours of preparation required to present accurate and well-informed views ... I must acknowledge that the whole process of offering views on matters of concern to the nation via the talk show circuit was most satisfying. It obliged me to keep on top of a variety of developments, and it was quite fulfilling to be asked my opinion on the issues of the day" (Evidence, p. 357). Many of these appearances with Thornburgh's handwritten notes in preparation are represented in these files and are particularly intriguing.
  Throughout these years Thornburgh has spoken around the country, frequently including a plea for involvement in public life. What Thornburgh describes as his most comprehensive review of this subject is the Webb Lecture to the National Academy of Public Administration (NAPA) in November 1998, which is available here online. To this group he stated: "Democracy is not a spectator sport. All of us must exercise the opportunity to contribute to improving and sustaining higher levels of performance in public life.
  In the fall of 2002, Thornburgh was appointed examiner in WorldCom bankruptcy, the largest in American history, resulting from nearly $11 billion misreported revenues and expenditures. The archive includes extensive documentation of this "massive task" and all three reports.
  The files in this ongoing section of Dick Thornburgh's career are in the following subseries: 1) Speeches and Testimony; 2) Transcripts; 3) Foreign Trips; 4) Events; 5) Professional and Civic Work; 6) Media Interviews; 7) Correspondence; 8) Articles and Issues; 9) Where the Evidence Leads; 10) Varied Subjects of Interest; 11) Three Mile Island; and 12) Awards and Honors.
  As Thornburgh continues his career more files are contributed to his archives ongoing. Stay tuned.
  - Speeches and Testimony, 1.
    Thornburgh's ongoing career, for archive purposes, began March 1993, just after his sojourn at the United Nations. Since that time, up to and including April 2004 there were over 100 speeches and testimonies which have been digitized and are available here online. In 2013 an additional 127 were added.
    In some respects, there is no better way to recognize the diversity and substance of Thornburgh's career than in reviewing these speeches and testimonies. There is a remarkably broad array of topics which relate to his many ongoing interests and commitments, for example: human rights, drug and alcohol abuse, business crime, rule of law, partnerships in science and technology, law enforcement, United Nations, merit selection for judges, civil justice reform, health care, Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), war against terrorism, disability and civil rights, Three Mile Island, crises in corporate America, WorldCom bankruptcy, and World Bank investigation. These were delivered, just for example, before Committees of Congress, at Graduations, at the Vatican Conference on Drug and Alcohol Abuse, to colleges and universities, bar associations, Chambers of Commerce and United Nations events.
    - Vatican Conference on Drug and Alcohol Abuse, Rome, Italy, November 23, 1991 (Box 984, Folder 1)
    - Statement before the Subcommittee on International Security, International Organizations and Human Rights of Committee on Foreign Affairs, House of Representatives: overview of experience at United Nations, Washington, DC, March 5, 1993 (Box 984, Folder 2)
    - Testimony before the United States House of Representatives Subcommittee on Commerce, Justice, State and Judiciary, Committee on Appropriations, Washington, DC, April 26, 1993 (Box 984, Folder 3)
    - Testimony before the United States Senate Subcommittee on Terrorism, Narcotics, and International Operations, Committee on Foreign Relations, Washington, DC, June 22, 1993 (Box 984, Folder 4)
    - Statement before the Joint Committee on the Organization of Congress, Washington, DC, June 22, 1993 (Box 984, Folder 5)
    - "The 1990s: America's Decade?" Robert A. and Thelma K. Gleason Lecture Series on American Politics and Government, St. Francis College, Loretto, PA, November 3, 1993 (Box 984, Folder 6)
    - Address to the Class of 1994, Graduate School of Public and International Affairs (GSPIA) of the University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, May 1, 1994 (Box 984, Folder 7)
    - "The American Century ... Revisited," Annual Dinner of the Yale Club of Montclair, Montclair, NJ, May 5, 1994 (Box 984, Folder 8)
    - Graduation Address to the Class of 1994 at Shippensburg University, Shippensburg, PA, May 7, 1994 (Box 984, Folder 9)
    - Graduation Address to the Class of 1994 at Clarion University, Clarion, PA, May 14, 1994 (Box 984, Folder 10)
    - "The Rule of Law in Hong Kong ... Today and Tomorrow," American Chamber of Commerce in Hong Kong, June 16, 1994 (Box 984, Folder 11)
    - "The Internationalization of Business Crime," Annual Business Luncheon of the Section of Business Law of the American Bar Association, New Orleans, LA, August 9, 1994 (Box 984, Folder 12)
    - "Partnerships in Science and Technology: New Paths to Prosperity," Annual Meeting of Franklin Chamber of Commerce, Franklin, PA, April 4, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 13)
    - Graduation Address to the Class of 1995 at Defiance College, Defiance, OH, May 7, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 14)
    - National Leadership Summit of the American Legislative Exchange Council (ALEC), Richmond, VA, May 18-21, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 15)
    - Statement before The United States Senate Committee on Foreign Relations, Subcommittee on East Asian and Pacific Affairs, Washington, DC, June 6, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 16)
    - "The Rule of Law in the Next Century," Pepperdine University Associates Dinner, Los Angeles, CA, June 8, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 17)
    - The Voices of Freedom: America Speaks out on Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA): A Forum Sponsored by the National Council on Disability on the Fifth Anniversary of the Signing of ADA, July 25, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 18)
    - "The State of the Rule of Law in America," Annual Mary Elizabeth Babcock Lecture, Denison University, Granville, OH, October 5, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 19)
    - "The Rule of Law Around the World," Friday Forum, Dallas, TX, October 13, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 20)
    - "U.N. Management and Mismanagement: Developing Sanctions and Better Oversight," Session III of American Leadership Conference, October 17, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 21)
    - "Business Crime Goes International," Yale Center for International and Area Studies, New Haven, CT, November 4, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 22)
    - Testimony before the U.S. House of Representatives Committee on the Judiciary, Subcommittee on Crime: Hearing on Nature, Extent, and Proliferation of Federal Law Enforcement, Washington, DC, November 15, 1995 (Box 984, Folder 23)
    - "Public-Private Partnerships in Science and Technology," Sigma XI Forum on Science Technology, and the Global Society, San Diego, CA, March 7, 1996 (Box 984, Folder 24)
    - Statement on Common Sense Product Liability Reform Act of 1996 (H.R. 956), April 30, 1996 (Box 984, Folder 25)
    - Testimony before the U.S. Senate Committee on the Judiciary: The Role of the American Bar Association in the Judicial Selection Process, Washington, DC, May 21, 1996 (Box 984, Folder 26)
    - "Commerce, Investment and the Rule of Law in the Russian Federation--What is to be Done?" U.S.-Russia Chamber of Commerce of Boston, Inc., Boston, MA, October 31, 1996 (Box 984, Folder 27)
    - Statement before the Hearing on the Roles and Responsibilities of the Secretary-General of the United Nations, United Nations Association of the United States of America, New York, NY, November 14, 1996 (Box 984, Folder 28)
    - "Technology, Partnerships, and the Economy," First Annual Stakeholders Meeting sponsored by the New York State Science and Technology Foundation, Saratoga Springs, NY, November 19, 1996 (Box 984, Folder 29)
    - "The Search for 'The Truth, the Whole Truth, and Nothing but the Truth,' in the Criminal Justice Process," 97th Annual Meeting of the Massachusetts Bar Association, Boston, MA, February 7, 1997 (Box 984, Folder 30)
    - Testimony before the U.S. House of Representatives Committee on International Relations, Subcommittee on East Asian and Pacific Affairs, Washington, DC, February 13, 1997 (Box 984, Folder 31)
    - "Business Crime Goes International," Honors College of the University of Southern Mississippi, Hattiesburgh, MS, April 29, 1997 (Box 984, Folder 32)
    - Graduation Address to the Class of 1997 at Shady Side Academy, Pittsburgh, PA, June 6, 1997 (Box 984, Folder 33)
    - "Junk Science--The Lawyer's Ethical Responsibilities," Fordham University School of Law, New York, NY, October 21, 1997 (Box 984, Folder 34)
    - "Artificial Entities and Artificial Crimes," Citizens against Government Waste, Hershey, PA, November 14, 1997 (Box 984, Folder 35)
    - "America's Challenges and Responsibilities in the 21st Century," San Joaquin Valley Town Hall, Fresno, CA, November 19, 1997 (Box 984, Folder 36)
    - "Science and Technology and the States," Conference on Understanding the Science and Technology Enterprise: the Political and Economic Context, Brookings Institution, Washington, DC, January 27, 1998 (Box 984, Folder 37)
    - "The University as a Useful Citizen," Honors Convocation of the University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, February 27, 1998 (Box 984, Folder 38)
    - Statement of the Former Attorneys Generals regarding the Independent Counsel Act, March 5, 1998 (Box 984, Folder 39)
    - "Constitutional Path to Self-Determination for Puerto Rico," Rotary Club of San Jan, San Juan, Puerto Rico, April 21, 1998 (Box 984, Folder 40)
    - Commencement Address to the 1998 Graduating Class of the University of Pittsburgh School of Law, Pittsburgh, PA, May 23, 1998 (Box 984, Folder 41)
    - "Law and Policy Under ADA: A Look Back and a Look Forward," Opening Plenary Session of "In Pursuit...a Blueprint for Disability Law and Policy," Commission on Mental and Physical Disability Law of the American Bar Association, Washington, DC, June 18, 1998 (Box 984, Folder 42)
    - "America's Challenges and Responsibilities in the 21st Century," 25th Anniversary Banquet of the National Decision Program at the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, November 7, 1998 (Box 984, Folder 43)
    - "'Doing the Right Thing' and 'Doing the Thing Right:' Five Themes for a New Millennium," Webb Lecture to the Annual Meeting of the National Academy of Public Administration, November 20, 1998 (Box 984, Folder 44)
    - "Resurrecting Justice: The Ethical Cost of Lawsuit Abuse," Manhattan Institute Conference, New York, NY, January 20, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 45)
    - "America's Challenges and Responsibilities in the 21st Century," Town Hall Speakers Series sponsored by the One Hundred, Savannah, GA, February 11, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 46)
    - "The Role of the Federal Government in Private Appellate Civil Litigation," Third National Litigation Conference of the Federal Bar Association, Las Vegas, NV, March 13, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 47)
    - "Some Reflections on Three Mile Island," Clarke Center for the Interdisciplinary Study of Contemporary Issues, Dickinson College, Carlisle, PA, March 25, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 48)
    - "Practicing Law in the Next Century: Ethics, Public Service and Professionalism," 75th Anniversary Observance of Sutherland, Asbill and Brennan LLP, White Sulphur Springs, WV, April 17, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 49)
    - Health Care Liability Alliance, Washington, DC, April 19, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 50)
    - "Remembering the Past, Recommitting to the Future," ARC Pennsylvania Annual Convention, Hidden Valley, PA, June 17, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 51)
    - "The Global Imperative: Why Your State Must be Involved in the World," to "Governing in a Global Age," A Fellowship Program for State and Local Officials conducted by Elliot School of International Affairs, George Washington University, Washington, DC, June 18, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 52)
    - "A Legal Reform Agenda for the Next Millennium," Richmond Lawyers Chapter of the Federalist Society, Richmond, VA, June 29, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 53)
    - "Violence and Youth Culture," Chairman's Advisory Board and President's Club of the Republican National Committee, Philadelphia, PA, July 7, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 54)
    - "Remembering the Past, Recommitting to the Future," Summer Training Session of the National Conference of Executives of the ARC, Lake Buena Vista, FL, July 28, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 55)
    - Testimony before the Subcommittee on Commercial and Administrative Law, Committee on the Judiciary, House of Representatives, Washington, DC, September 15, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 56)
    - "State Technology Initiatives in the United States," Second Transatlantic Technology Forum: Perspectives of Change sponsored by Technolgiestiftung Schleswig-Holstein, Lubeck, Germany, October 4, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 57)
    - "Sharing Some Thoughts on David Ehrenwerth's Lifetime of Service to His Community," Pittsburgh Chapter of the American Jewish Committee, Pittsburgh, PA, December 15, 1999 (Box 984, Folder 58)
    - "Reflection on the Americans with Disabilities Act," Gardere Wynne Sewell and Riggs Lecture, University of Houston Law Center, Health, Law and Policy Institute, Houston, TX, February 24, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 59)
    - "America's Challenges and Responsibilities in the 21st Century," Fox Chapel Town Hall, Pittsburgh, PA, April 13, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 60)
    - "The Americans with Disabilities Act: How Far Have We Come in the First Decade? What are the Leadership Imperatives for the Next?" DEED 2000 Conference, Empire State College, State University of New York, Rochester, NY, April 30, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 61)
    - "Law and Values for America's Future," Law Day Luncheon of the Jacksonville Bar Association, Jacksonville, FL, May 10, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 62)
    - Senate Judiciary Committee Dinner, Washington, DC, May 17, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 63)
    - "Core Values--Important or Not? The Public Sector Perspective," 2000 Annual Meeting of the Physicians Insurance Association of America, Washington, DC, June 1, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 64)
    - "It's Time for a Federal Criminal Code," Annual Meeting of the Federal Bar Association, Cleveland, OH, September 21, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 65)
    - Statement regarding H.R. 4751 before the Committee on Resources, U.S. House of Representatives, Washington, DC (with attachments), October 4, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 66)
    - "America's Challenges and Responsibilities in the 21st Century," J. Howard Pew Memorial Lecture, Grove City College, Grove City, PA, October 9, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 67)
    - "Disability and Civil Rights: Remembering the Past, Recommitting to the Future," 51st Annual Convention of the ARC, Birmingham, AL, October 12, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 68)
    - "Violence in America: Challenges to our Institutions," Conference on "Violence in America: Divergent Perspectives," Millersville University, Millersville, PA, November 9, 2000 (Box 984, Folder 69)
    - "Challenges to Lawyers and the Law," University of Pittsburgh School of Law, Law Review and Journal of Law and Commerce Banquet, Pittsburgh, PA, March 13, 2001 (Box 984, Folder 70)
    - "Science and Technology and Economic Growth in the 21st Century: The Challenge to the States," 21st Century Fund Coalition Spring Luncheon, Indianapolis, IN, March 27, 2001 (Box 984, Folder 71)
    - "Of Lawyers and the Law," University of Iowa College of Law Commencement, Iowa City, IA, May 12, 2001 (Box 984, Folder 72)
    - "Disabilities and Civil Rights: The Challenges of Empowerment," Membership Appreciation Luncheon of the ARC of Northern Virginia, Vienna, VA, July 20, 2001 (Box 984, Folder 73)
    - "Tools for the Fight against Corruption," Colloquium on "Ethics, Accountability and Social Responsibility: A Transatlantic Perspective," Transatlantic Consortium for Public Policy Analysis and Education, GSPIA, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, September 21, 2001 (Box 984, Folder 74)
    - "What Role for the U.N. in the War Against Terrorism," Assembly 2001: Search for Solutions to Critical Global Problems, World Association of Non-Governmental Organizations and Interreligious and International Federation for World Peace, New York, NY, October 21, 2001 (Box 984, Folder 75)
    - "Observations," A Virtual Retreat of Kirkpatrick and Lockhart LLP, Washington, DC, October 26, 2001 (Box 984, Folder 76)